Scenic Hudson Decision Hearings Transcripts Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Scenic Hudson Decision Hearings Transcripts Collection
March 9, 1977 - December 12, 1980
NPkMC-222-083
10.5 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
The Hudson River Fisheries Unit
Scenic Hudson was created in 1963 and became well known through its fight to save Storm King Mountain. In 1963, Con Edison developed a proposal to build the world’s largest pumped-storage hydroelectric plant. The Hudson River Conservation Society Collection features the EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System hearings. These hearings span over 3 years, containing information on the legal dispute and the efforts that were made to fight against Con Edison.
Collection Overview
The Scenic Hudson Collection consists of materials documenting the landmark environmental law case that opposed the Consolidated Edison Company’s proposed pump storage facility at Storm King Mountain, near Cornwall, NY. The Scenic Hudson Decision, as the case is called in law books, launched the modern environmental movement. The collection consists of transcripts of hearings from March 9, 1977 to December 12, 1980. These hearing are titled, EPA National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System. This case was brought before Judge Thomas B. Yost. Present for the hearings were Henry Gluckstern, Attorney for EPA, Region II, Jonathan Strong, Attorney for EPA, E.J. Sack Attorney for Con Edison as well as many others. The hearings concluded on December 12, 1980 where Con Edison agreed to drop the plan for the Storm King facility.
Acquisitions Information
The Hudson River Fisheries Unit donated the collection to the Marist College Library in 2008.
Historical Note
In September 1962, the Consolidated Edison Company announced plans to build a pumped storage facility, the largest of its kind in the world, at Storm King Mountain near Cornwall, New York. The initial application for license to construct the plant was filed with the Federal Power Commission in January 1963. On November 8, 1963, a small group of concerned citizens met at the home of Carl Carmer and formed the Scenic Hudson Preservation Conference to fight the pumped storage project on the grounds that it posed a threat to the Cornwall water supply and Hudson River fisheries as well as to scenic and historic Storm King Mountain.
Carl Carmer, author of The Hudson River and other historic works, became honorary chairman and Leo O. Rothchild was named chairman. Rothchild served until 1968 and was succeeded by Alexander Saunders. Initially, the members, working in their own homes or borrowed office space, contacted friends, prominent citizens, politicians, and other organizations for financial support, letter writing campaigns, and legal intervention. The organizations grew rapidly. Contributions were channeled through the Natural Area Council until Scenic Hudson was incorporated in 1974. Rod Vandivert became the executive director in the mid-1960s. An office was set up in New York City, but the location changed several times during Storm King case and there were a number of office managers during that period. Professional fundraisers and public relations firms were employed in later years.
Aided by other organizations and individuals, the group conducted an intensive campaign to educate the public and to deter Consolidated Edison by legal means. The records, which document the organization’s activities, include publicity materials, copies of legal documents submitted by Scenic Hudson and others, and transcripts of hearings before Congressional sub-committees and the Federal Power Commission. The case lasted for 17 years. In a negotiated settlement in December 1980, Consolidated Edison agreed to drop the plan for the Storm King facility.
The lengthy and controversial case set important precedents in environmental law and is generally credited with spawning the modern environmental movement. Scenic Hudson, Inc. continues to serve as an environmental watchdog in the Hudson Valley.
There are no restrictions on this collection
Collection is arranged into two series: 1. Hearings, 2. Miscellaneous
Materials are arranged chronologically.
- 1. Hearings, 1; 10.0 linear feet 1 - 7 1 - 124
  This case was brought before Judge Thomas B. Yost. Present for the hearings were Henry Gluckstern, Attorney for EPA, Region II, Jonathan Strong, Attorney for EPA, E.J. Sack Attorney for Con Edison as well as many others. The hearings all took place in New York City, with the majority of them being held at the World Trade Center.
  Chronological
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 8, 1977, 2585 - 2751 (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 8, 1977, 2585 - 2751 (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 10, 1977, 2922 - 3033 (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 7, 1977, 78 - 257 (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 8, 1977, 258 - 450 (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 12, 1977, 451 - 566 (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 13, 1977, 567 - 754 (Folder 7, Box 2)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 14, 1977, 755 - 915 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 15, 1977, 916 - 1089 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 16, 1977, 1090 - 1214 (Folder 10, Box 2)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 14, 1978, 1215 - 1420 (Folder 11, Box 2)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 15, 1978, 1421 - 1621 (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 16, 1978, 1622 - 1792 (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 28, 1978, 1793 - 1984 (Folder 14, Box 3)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 1, 1978, 1984 - 2156 (Folder 15, Box 3)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 2, 1978, 2157 - 2346 (Folder 16, Box 3)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 3, 1978, 3247 - 2420 (Folder 17, Box 4)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 6, 1978, 2421 - 2584 (Folder 18, Box 4)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 7, 1978, 2421 - 2584 (Folder 19, Box 4)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 9, 1978, 2752 - 2921 (Folder 20, Box 4)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 23, 1978, 3346 - 3535 (Folder 21, Box 4)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 24, 1978, 3536 - 3652 (Folder 22, Box 4)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 18, 1978 ,3653 - 3829 (Folder 23, Box 5)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 18, 1978, 3653 - 3829 (Folder 24, Box 5)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 19, 1978, 3830 - 3991 (Folder 25, Box 5)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 19, 1978, 3830 - 3991 (Folder 26, Box 5)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 20, 1978, 4002 - 4170 (Folder 27, Box 5)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 20, 1978, 4002 - 4170 (Folder 28, Box 6)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 21, 1978, 4171 - 4306 (Folder 29, Box 6)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, April 21, 1978, 4171 - 4306 (Folder 30, Box 6)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 9, 1978, 4307 - 4489 (Folder 31, Box 6)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 9, 1978, 4307 - 4489 (Folder 32, Box 6)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 10, 1978, 4490 - 4659 (Folder 33, Box 7)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 10, 1978, 4490 - 4569 (Folder 34, Box 7)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 11, 1978, 4660 - 4838 (Folder 35, Box 7)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 11, !978, 4660 - 4838 (Folder 36, Box 7)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 12, 1978, 4839 - 5000 (Folder 37, Box 7)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, May 12, 1978, 4839 - 5000 (Folder 38, Box 8)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 6, 1978, 5001 - 5199 (Folder 39, Box 8)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 7, 1978, 5200 - 5400 (Folder 40, Box 8)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 8, 1978, 5401 - 5593 (Folder 41, Box 8)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 9, 1978, 5594 - 5723 (Folder 42, Box 8)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 9, 1978, 5724 - 5930 (Folder 43, Box 9)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 22, 1978, 5931 - 6117 (Folder 44, Box 9)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 23, 1978, 6119 - 6205 (Folder 45, Box 9)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 26, 1978, 6206 - 6375 (Folder 46, Box 9)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 27, 1978, 6376 - 6544 (Folder 47, Box 9)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 28, 1978, 6545 - 6770 (Folder 48, Box 9)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 29, 1978, 6771 - 6883 (Folder 49, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 19, 1978, 6884 - 7040 (Folder 50, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 20, 1978, 7041 - 7180 (Folder 51, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 21, 1978, 7181 - 7310 (Folder 52, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 22, 1978, 7311 - 7433 (Folder 53, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 3, 1978, 7434 - 7589 (Folder 54, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 4, 1978, 7590 - 7750 (Folder 55, Box 10)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 5, 1978, 7751 - 7925 (Folder 56, Box 11)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 6, 1978, 7926 - 8035 (Folder 57, Box 11)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 17, 1978, 8036 - 8229 (Folder 58, Box 11)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 18, 1978, 8230 - 8399 (Folder 59, Box 11)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 19, 1978, 8400 - 8615 (Folder 60, Box 11)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 20, 1978, 8616 - 8739 (Folder 61, Box 11)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 31, 1978, 8731 - 8910 (Folder 62, Box 12)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 1, 1978, 8911 - 9095 (Folder 63, Box 12)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 2, 1978, 9096 - 9281 (Folder 64, Box 12)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 3, 1978, 9282 - 9451 (Folder 65, Box 12)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 14, 1978, 9452 - 9535 (Folder 66, Box 12)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 27, 1978, 9536 - 9715 (Folder 67, Box 12)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 28, 1978, 9716 - 9896 (Folder 68, Box 13)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 29, 1978, 9897 - 10,070 (Folder 69, Box 13)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 30, 1978, 10071 - 100268 (Folder 70, Box 13)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 1, 1978, 10270 - 104441 (Folder 71, Box 13)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 14, 1978, 10442 - 10536 (Folder 72, Box 13)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 15, 1978, 10537 - 10739 (Folder 73, Box 13)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, January 24, 1979, 10740 - 10903 (Folder 74, Box 14)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 7, 1979, 14682 - 14832 (Folder 75, Box 14)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 12, 1979, 10904 - 11073 (Folder 76, Box 14)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 13, 1979, 11074 - 11242 (Folder 77, Box 14)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 14, 1979, 11243 - 11424 (Folder 78, Box 14)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, June 15, 1979, 11425 - 11526 (Folder 79, Box 14)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 10, 1979, 11526 - 11727 (Folder 80, Box 15)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 11, 1979, 11728 - 11956 (Folder 81, Box 15)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 12, 1979, 11957 - 12117 (Folder 82, Box 15)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 13, 1979, 12118 - 12184 (Folder 83, Box 15)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, August 13, 1979, 17277 - 17506 (Folder 84, Box 15)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, August 14, 1979, 17507 - 17809 (Folder 85, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 18, 1979, 12185 - 12314 (Folder 86, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 19, 1979, 12315 - 12503 (Folder 87, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 20, 1979, 12504 - 12598 (Folder 88, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 21, 1979, 12599 - 12678 (Folder 89, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 3, 1979 12679 - 12877 (Folder 90, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 3, 1979, 12679 - 12877 (Folder 91, Box 16)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, November 29, 1979, 13282 - 13466 (Folder 92, Box 17)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 10, 1979, 19685 - 19917 (Folder 93, Box 17)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 17, 1979, 12595 - 13797 (Folder 94, Box 17)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 18, 1979, 13798 - 13946 (Folder 95, Box 17)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 19, 1979, 13947 - 14116 (Folder 96, Box 17)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 20, 1979, 14117 - 14299 (Folder 97, Box 18)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 5, 1980, 14300 - 14513 (Folder 98, Box 18)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 6, 1980, 14514 - 14681 (Folder 99, Box 18)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 19, 1980, 14833 - 14988 (Folder 100, Box 18)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 20, 1980, 14989 - 15165 (Folder 101, Box 18)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 21, 1980, 15166 - 15382 (Folder 102, Box 19)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, February 22, 1980, 15383 - 15457 (Folder 103, Box 19)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 26, 1980, 15928 - 16085 (Folder 104, Box 19)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 27, 1980, 16086 - 16207 (Folder 105, Box 19)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, March 28, 1980, 16208 - 16311 (Folder 106, Box 19)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 8 1980, 16349 - 16517 (Folder 107, Box 19)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 9, 1980, 16519 - 16707 (Folder 108, Box 20)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 10, 1980, 16709 - 16884 (Folder 109, Box 20)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, July 11, 1980, 16885 - 17032 (Folder 110, Box 20)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, August 12, 1980, 17060 - 17276 (Folder 111, Box 20)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, August 15, 1980, 17671 - 17802 (Folder 112, Box 20)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 16, 1980, 17803 - 18000 (Folder 113, Box 21)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 17, 1980, 18001 - 18186 (Folder 114, Box 21)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 18, 1980, 18187 - 18301 (Folder 115, Box 21)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, September 25, 1980, 18302 - 18488 (Folder 116, Box 21)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 7, 1980, 18489 - 18696 (Folder 117, Box 21)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 8, 1980, 18697 - 18897 (Folder 118, Box 22)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 9, 1980, 18898 - 19062 (Folder 119, Box 22)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 10, 1980, 19063 - 19212 (Folder 120, Box 22)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 21, 1980, 19213 - 19481 (Folder 121, Box 22)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, October 22, 1980, 19482 - 19684 (Folder 122, Box 22)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 11, 1980, 19918 - 20145 (Folder 123, Box 23)
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, December 12, 1980, 20146 - 20294 (Folder 124, Box 23)
- 2. Miscellaneous Folder, 2; 0.5 linear feet 7 125
  This folder includes evidence that was used during the hearings. There is a letter to Mr. Mark concerning the First Set of Interrogatories Respecting EPA Exhibit 218 Appendix 1 from Jonathan Strong, and a letter to Judge Yost concerning Submittal of Errata with Respect to Exhibit EPA – 200.
  - EPA, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, MISC. FOLDER (Evidence) (Folder 125, Box 23)